Rahul Murmuria

10524 Rosehaven Street, Apt. 204, Fairfax, VA 22030 Email: rahul@murmuria.in | Phone: (703) 474-1261

Profile

Researcher and innovator with 10 years of diversified professional experience in software engineering, data science, and human factors. Ph.D. candidate in Computer Science at George Mason University, Fairfax, Virginia. Co-inventor of a patent-applied technology to continuously authenticate users on a smartphone by modeling their physical behavior using machine learning techniques. First author in 2 peer-reviewed conference papers and 2 workshop papers, and co-authored various other conference papers, white papers, grant proposals, and tutorials.

Professional Experience

Kryptowire, Fairfax, VA Research Engineer June 2015-present

- Lead the Continuous Authentication project while developing the analytics and software implementation which leverages user's physical behavior to revise a trust score that represents how certain the smartphone is that the user is legitimate
- Designed the data collection process involving 110 participants, prepared analytics using a variety of standard and non-standard machine learning algorithms, and contributed to the grant proposal and final report
- Implemented a proof-of-concept on Android devices that performs data collection, model generation, and continuous authentication score computation entirely on-device (Patent filed)

Center for Assurance Research and Engineering, Fairfax, VA Research Assistant

January 2010–May 2015

- Prepared a regression based model on Android smartphones to predict battery power consumption using multi-dimensional system resources measurements, achieving a granularity of as low as 1 kernel jiffy in time
- Conducted performance analysis of a custom fuse-based encrypted filesystem for Android devices; Developed the login process and the secure-wipe which was deployed by DARPA into devices used by the military
- Supervised Ph.D. students to create a user input record-and-replay tool for Android devices to test user interfaces by repeating the same sequence of inputs at different speeds controlled by a script

Federal Trade Commission, Washington D.C.

May 2013–July 2013

- Tech Intern
 - Provided technical expertise and guidance as the FTC attorneys performed research in the mobile app stores and analyzed potentially fraudulent mobile applications
 - Developed ways to automate some of the processes of preparing technical evidence

George Mason University, Fairfax, VA

August 2012–May 2013

Teaching Assistant

• Conducted classroom lectures and prepared homework assignments for graduate-level courses: Security Lab, Intrusion Detection, Network Security, and OS Security

George Mason University, Fairfax, VA

October 2008–January 2010

System Administrator (Graduate Assistant)

• Provided second tier technical support to the School of Engineering

 $Openworld,\ Washington\ D.C.$

September 2005-May 2007

Offshore Web Developer

• Built a web portal for online marketplace of telework services

Education

 $Doctorate\ of\ Philosophy\ in\ Computer\ Science,\ GPA\ 3.54\ (All\ But\ Dissertation)$

January 2011–Summer 2017

George Mason University, Fairfax, VA

Proposal - Modeling User Behavior for Context Generation on Mobile Devices

Master of Science in Computer Engineering, GPA 3.8

August 2008–December 2010

George Mason University, Fairfax, VA

Thesis - Energy Profiling and Control for Android Devices

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Engineering, GPA 7.08 / 10.0 $\,$

July 2004–May 2008

National Institute of Technology, Jaipur, India Project - Glendix: A Plan 9 / Linux Distribution

Selected Coursework

Quantitative Methods in Computer Science, Theory and Applications of Data Mining, Advanced Artificial Intelligence, Concurrent Software Systems, Operating Systems Security, Distributed Systems, Advanced Computer Networks

Patents

A. Stavrou, R. Murmuria, R. Johnson, D. Barbara. Active Authentication of Users. USPTO Application 15236049, filed August 2016. Patent Pending.

Publications

Peer-Reviewed Conference Papers

- 1. R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou, D. Barbara, D. Fleck. Continuous Authentication on Mobile Devices Using Power Consumption, Touch Gestures and Physical Movement of Users. Research in Attacks, Intrusions, and Defenses (RAID), pp. 405–424. Springer, 2015.
- 2. R. Murmuria, J. Medsger, A. Stavrou, J.M. Voas. Mobile Application and Device Power Usage Measurements. Sixth International Conference on Software Security and Reliability (SERE), pp. 147–156. IEEE, 2012.
- 3. Z. Wang, R. Johnson, R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou. Exposing Security Risks for Commercial Mobile Devices. *International Conference on Mathematical Methods, Models, and Architectures for Computer Network Security (MMM-ACNS)*, pp. 3–21. Springer, 2012.
- 4. Z. Wang, R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou. Implementing and optimizing an encryption filesystem on android. 13th International Conference on Mobile Data Management (MDM), pp. 52–62. IEEE, 2012.

Workshop Papers

- R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou, D. Barbara, V. Sritapan. Your Data in Your Hands: Privacy-preserving User Behavior Models for Context Computation. International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications (PerCom), IEEE, 2017.
- 6. R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou. Authentication Feature and Model Selection using Penalty Algorithms. Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security (SOUPS), USENIX, 2016.

White Papers

- 7. R. Martin, R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou, N. Nazzicari. MokA: Mobile k-Anonymity (Sender Anonymity Over Untrusted Mobile Network Operators). 2010.
- 8. M. S. Gaur, A. Narayanan, R. Murmuria. Comparative Analytic Simulation of Peer to Peer Networks. 2007.

Tutorials

- 9. R. Johnson, R. Murmuria, A. Stavrou, V. Sritapan. Pairing Continuous Authentication with Proactive Platform Hardening. *International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications (PerCom)*, IEEE, 2017.
- 10. A. Narayanan, R. Narasimhan, R. Murmuria, M. Gaur. Institutional Information Management using Open Source Technologies. 1st International Conference on Digital Information Management, IEEE, 2006.

Computing Skills

Programming and Markup Languages: Python, Java, R, LaTeX, Bash, C++, PHP, SQL, Javascript, Lisp

Data Manipulation: MySQL, SQLite, Pandas, HDF5, CSV, JSON, XML

Statistical Analysis Tools: Scikit-learn, Weka, Matlab, Apache Commons Math, Eigen

Visualization Tools: Matplotlib, Seaborn, Tableau, Gnuplot

Other Tools and API: Beautiful Soup, Cake PHP, Snort, Wireshark, Valgrind, Callgrind, gprof

Volunteering

National Institute of Technology, Jaipur, India

2005-2008

- Co-created a hands-on weekend workshop series on system administration, web scripting, and general programming;
 Mentored junior students to actively take up open source development
- Developed the University's first electronic course registration system which included some back-office functions, thereby saving the faculty, staff, and students 5000+ man-hours every semester